<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mr. Thomas Pury alderman of Glocester his speech, upon that clause of the bill against episcopacy, the which concernes deanes, and deanes and chapters, at a committee of the whole House.</title>
            <author>Pury, Thomas, ca. 1590-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91369</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4247</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E198_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14642</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859711</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859711</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111807</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91369)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111807)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 35:E198[21])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mr. Thomas Pury alderman of Glocester his speech, upon that clause of the bill against episcopacy, the which concernes deanes, and deanes and chapters, at a committee of the whole House.</title>
                  <author>Pury, Thomas, ca. 1590-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 9, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Episcopacy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111807:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 109 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:111807:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 109 -->
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">R</hi>: THOMAS PVRY ALDERMAN OF GLOCESTER his SPEECH, UPON That clauſe of the <hi>Bill</hi> againſt <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> the which Concernes <hi>Deanes,</hi> and <hi>Deanes</hi> and <hi>Chapters,</hi> at a COMMITTEE of the whole <hi>HOVSE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the yeare 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:111807:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 110 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111807:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 110 -->
            <head>M<hi rend="sup">R</hi>. THOMAS PVRY <hi>Alderman</hi> of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> his SPEECH, Vpon that Clauſe of the <hi>Bill</hi> againſt EPISCOPACY; the which concernes DEANES, and DEANES and CHAPTERS at a <hi>Committee</hi> of the whole <hi>Houſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. HIDE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Riſe not up to Anſwer the Arguments of the Learned Gentleman of the long robe that ſpake laſt, the which were to prove ſome Inco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence of the Preamble with the body of the Bill concerning the aboliſhing of Deanes and Chapters in reſpect of their government in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who have none at all, as hath beene argued, but there are ſome Reaſons ſticke with me, whereby I doe conceive, that the Deanes and Chapters have beene, and are
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111807:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 111 -->part of the Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and that the preamble, and body of this Bill, therein may very well ſtand together; for if you take the Deanes and Chapters in their Originall, who (as it was ſaid by a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Sergeant over againſt me) were firſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in ſuperſtition alike to your Regular and Secular Monkes; or if you conſider them as in their prime inſtitution to be <hi>Conſilium Epiſ.</hi> to aſſiſt Biſhops in their Government and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline; or if you looke upon thoſe Deanes and Chapters of the laſt Foundation by <hi>Henry the eight:</hi> yet certainely they are in all theſe capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities a part of the government of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and as well the Rurall, as the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall Deanes are numbred by our owne Writers among Church Governors, and they are in and among themſelves a part of the Church Government, and by the Booke of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Eccleſiaſticall Lawes they are to governe themſelves according to their Statutes of Foundation, and to keepe them pure and entire, ſo farre as they are not repugnant to the Word of God, and our Conſtitutions of Religion. And for the better Satisfaction of this Committee and my ſelfe, here is a Copy of the Statutes Grant, and Foundation of the Deane and Chapter of the city of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> I have read them over, and doe finde, firſt the end wherefore the Lands and Poſſeſſions were granted unto them. Secondly, the manner and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111807:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 111 -->forme of Gevernment of themſelves. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, their ſeverall Oathes to keepe all the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes preſcribed unto them: And becauſe of my weake memory, pleaſe you to give me leave to reade the words in the Kings Grant, <hi>Engliſhed</hi> thus;</p>
            <p>Wee have erected and conſtituted Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dralls and Colleges in the place of Monaſteries, to the end, that where Ignorance, and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition did raigne there; the ſinceere Worſhip of God ſhould flouriſh, and the holy Goſpell of Chriſt Ieſus ſhould be dayly and purely Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. And further, that the increaſe of the Chriſtian Faith and Piety, the inſtruction of youth in good learning, and the ſuſtentation of the poore ſhould be for ever there kept, maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; continued; and the ſaid Deane, Prebends, Cannons, and all other perſons belonging to the ſaid Cathedralls and Colledges, are to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned and ruled according to the Statutes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed unto them.</p>
            <p>Sir, the Statutes are many, I will in briefe tell you the ſubſtance of ſome few af them. The ſaid Deane, Prebends, and Canons, are alwayes to reſide and dwell in the houſes of the ſaid Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrialls, and there to keep a Family, good ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitality, to feede the poore, and to diſtribute Almes unto the needy, to be carefull to Preach the Word of God, <hi>In ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon,</hi> and to ſow the ſeede of the Word of God abroad but eſpecially in the ſaid Cathedrall Church,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111807:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 112 -->and to have youth profitable taught there. And to the end that they may all ſerve God, as well at meales as in the Church, they are to have a common Table in the common Hall of the ſaid Cathedrall, where the ſaid Cannons Schollers, Quireſters, and under-Officers, are appointed to eate together, and the ſaid Deane and Chapter, are to give yearely twenty pound to the poore, beſide their owne poore Almſmen, and twenty pound more yearely to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the repairing of Bridges and High-wayes thereabouts.</p>
            <p>Sir, for the performance of the ſaid Statutes and premiſes. The ſaid Deane, Prebends Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons and Miniſters of the ſaid Cathedrall doe, or ought reſpectively to take an Oath; and thereby in expreſſe words do call God to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and doe ſweare upon the holy Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, to rule, governe and behave themſelves well and faithfully in the ſaid Church, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Will and Statutes of the Founder, and every one of them doe ſweare, that he will to his utmoſt power well and faithfully keepe all and ſingular the ſaid Ordinances &amp; Statutes, as much as concernes himſelfe, and will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure all others as much as concernes them to keepe the ſame inviolablely, So helpe him God, and theſe holy Goſpels of God.</p>
            <p>Mr. HIDE, You ſee wherefore the Lands were granted unto Deanes and Chapters, what
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111807:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 112 -->their Statutes are, and their Oathes to keepe them: It might be thought that theſe men doe know no way, another, or nearer way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven than they teach us; or otherwiſe that they would not ſit in the ſeate of Perjury, as it may ſteme they doe, without remorſe of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: For it is notoriouſly knowne to the city of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> and country there abouts, That not one of the ſaid Statutes before mentioned, are, or ever were, during my remembrance, kept, or the matters contained in any of them performed by any of the Deanes or Prebends of the ſaid Cathedrall; They come indeede once a yeare to receive the Rents and Profits of the ſaid Lands, but doe not deſtribute unto the poore and needy their portion, neglecting al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together the mending of the Highwayes and Bridges, and doe not keepe any common Table at all: and in ſtead of Preaching the Word of God themſelves, <hi>In ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon,</hi> they are, and have beene the chiefe inſtruments to hinder the ſame in others. Infinite are the Preſſure that many Cities neare unto Deanes and Chapters, have endured by them, and their procurement. And whereas it was objected by another learned Gentleman of the long robe, That the Deanes and Chapters are a body corporate, and that they have as much right unto their Lay poſſeſſions as any other body politicke, or any City or Towne Corporate; I am of his opinion, for ſuch Lands and Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111807:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 113 -->(if they have any) which they bought themſelves in right of their corporation, or for ſuch Lands as were given them for their owne uſe, and I am well contented that ſuch Lands ſhould be left unto them; but their caſe is farre different in my opinion; for I have ſhewed you before, to what godly, pious, and charitable uſes the ſaid Lands and poſſeſſions were gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto them: And ſutable thereunto you may call to minde the <hi>Londoners</hi> Caſe about <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donderry</hi> in the <hi>Starrechamber,</hi> where they were fyned 70000. pound to his Majeſtie, and the ſame afterwards eſtrated into his Majeſties Exchequer. But upon the Writ of Extent iſſuing out thereupon, his Majeſtie, as I have heard, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived no benefit of any ſuch Lands, wherof the Corporation was ſeized for the maintainance of any Hoſpitalls, Bridges, or other charitable uſes, or ought to have done, as I conceive. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore the ſaid Deanes and Chapters are but Truſtees, and the profits of the ſaid Lands, ſo ill imployed by them, contrary to the truſt repoſed in them; I am cleare of opinion, that by a Legiſlative power in <hi>Parliament,</hi> it is fit to take them away, and to put them into the hands of Feoffees to be diſpoſed of to ſuch pious, riligious, and charitable uſes, as they were firſt intended: But it was ſaid by a worthy Knight, That hee ſhould be unwilling to take away their Lands and Poſſeſſions, untill he firſt knew how they ſhould be diſpoſed of, and how the perſons,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111807:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 113 -->who were many thouſands in this Kingdome (as he ſaid) that would want bread, ſhould be provided for. Certainely Mr. <hi>Hide</hi> (although that is not the worke at this time) yet I account it no difficulty to ſatisfie that worthy Knight; for I finde upon the ſurvay of the Lands of the ſaid Deanery of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> that it hath above twelve Rectoryes of good value, &amp; about thirty Vicaredges, Pentions, and Portions of Tithes, which being at the firſt, <hi>Deo conſecraota,</hi> moſt fit they ſhould be ſtill imployed for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Goſpell; and therefore if thoſe Deanes and Prebends being but ſeaven in all to be now taken away, will be Preaching Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, there is, I hope, ſufficient maintenance for ſo many of them as have not too much, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides and yet to reſerve as large a Salary as now they have for ſo many ſinging men there in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Orders that cannot Preach. And then there are left to be provided for, but the Organiſt, eight Singing boyes, two Schoole-Maſters, foure poore Almeſmen, and ſome under-Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, whoſe yearely wages, comes unto about one hundred pound <hi>per annum;</hi> and the ſaid Deane and Chapter have almoſt the third part of the houſes of the City of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> the old rent of them being yearly about 175. pound, which will well defray that charge with a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Surpluſage for repairing the highwayes, Bridges; and twenty pound yearely to the poore, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:111807:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 114 -->
            <p>But over and beſides, the ſaid yearely reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes before mentioned, the ſaid Deane and Chapter of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> although but of the laſt Foundation, and one of the leaſt revenewes in this Kingdome, yet they have eighteene good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mannors, and alſo divers other Lands, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements, and Hereditaments, beſides the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors houſes, and premiſes, the old rent of Aſſize of one of the ſaid Mannors being 80. pound <hi>per annum;</hi> out of which Mannors and Lands, the ſaid Cathedrall being to be made a Perochicall Church 200. pound <hi>per annum,</hi> or more may be allowed for a learned Preaching Miniſter there, and a hundred pound a yeare apeice, for two ſuch others to aſſiſt him, with in few yeares, one of the ſaid Mannors will diſcharge, and alſo ſmfficiently repaire the ſaid Cathedrall Church; and then the reſt of the ſaid Mannors and Lands may be imployed to other godly, pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, or charitable uſes, as the Wiſedome of the King and Parliament ſhall thinke fit, and ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to this, but in a more ample proportion of maintenance, will be the allowances of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Deaneryes in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, this I conceive will anſwer another Objection raiſed by a worthy Knight at the Bar touching the poverty of the Clergy of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> if this Bill ſhould take effect, ſurely my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is quite contrary; and to that purpoſe, I call to minde the ſaying of a learned Divine, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine to a Noble man, upon ſome conference
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111807:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 114 -->with him of our wiſhed deſire to remove ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Miniſters, and to reduce the Impropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Biſhops, and Deanes and Chapters to a Preaching Miniſtry, if theſe things, ſaid hee, take effect, the Univerſities, will not be able to ſupply the Churches: And ſurely Sir, if theſe things take effect, I am confident we ſhall be ſo farre from having a poore beggerly Clergy, as that no Kingdome in the Chriſtian world will have a more rich, and flouriſhing Clergy, both for Nurſeries, and incouragements of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: and for their maintenance in more plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull manner than it is at this preſent. Pleaſe you therefore to put the Queſtion, I am ready to give my ayde thereunto.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
